<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A loving salutation to all people who have any desires after the living God but especially to the free-will-Anabaptists / from ... I. Beevan.</title>
            <author>Beevan, J. (John)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12643692</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12643692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 974:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A loving salutation to all people who have any desires after the living God but especially to the free-will-Anabaptists / from ... I. Beevan.</title>
                  <author>Beevan, J. (John)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65082:1"/>
            <head>A LOVING SALUTATION To all People who have any deſires after the Living GOD; But eſpecially to the Free-Will-ANABAPTISTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>From one that deſires the Eternal good of all Souls.</p>
                  <bibl>I. BEEVAN.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I was meditating on the wayes and works of the Lord, I can truly ſay my meditation of him was ſweet; for now I have found him whom my Soul long thirſted after in <hi>Egypt</hi> Land: I ſay as I was meditating there was brought by the power of the Lord a perfect remembrance of my ſore Travel in that dark Land of Bondage, now praiſes, praiſes to his great Name for ever, who hath ſent Redemption to Iſrael, and ſet the oppreſſed free, and broken that heavy yoak, and laid on his yoak that is eaſie, and his burthen which is light. Now in bowels of tender love to thoſe that know me by face and name in the outward, who hath been with me in many Trials, and yet are reſting there ſtill in that which will not ſtand in the day of the Lords power, when no covering will ſerve but the Spirit of the Lord; Now if you will but ſink down to that which is pure of God, and ſee and feel your ſelves and me alſo, and let that of God judge of my Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the way from thence, as the Lord God by his mighty power ſhall give me to relate.</p>
            <p>That the Truth of God may flouriſh, is the earneſt deſire of my Soul, &amp; that he may be exalted above all; Therefore I ſhall relate a little of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65082:2"/>long ſuffering of the Lord, and how unwilling he is that ſinners ſhould periſh, and alſo to make known to you that it is the ſame God I now own that brought me out of my mothers womb, and gave me life and all things.</p>
            <p>Near about the time that I was ſeven years of age, being bred up by my Parents very exactly for refraining of groſs evils, as Swearing and Curſing and the like; I can truly ſay that there was a greater Power reſtrained me then their words, and many deſires were raiſed up in me to know that God they talked of ſo much, and ſo often prayed to, and when I often asked where he was, and how he muſt be ſerved, they ſaid he was in Heaven above the Skies, but I felt him near me, reproving me for my playing and wantonneſs, as Children do practice in that nature; and many a vow I made not to do ſo again, but my vows I did not keep until I came near to fourteen years of age, then was the Lord pleaſed to ſhew his power yet more in reproving me for ſports and pleaſure, to which I hearkned a little &amp; did refrain it; yet there was ſomething in me luſted to ſee thoſe things acted which I could not do my ſelf; then I was judged for that alſo; then did I quite ſeparate my ſelf from my Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which reproach't me, but I matter'd them not, and I went along with a little flock in <hi>Leominſter,</hi> called <hi>Puretans,</hi> and many a faſt day I kept very exactly, and with the ſufferer I took part; then began my Parents to hate me when I was got above them, &amp; I denyed their formal prayers, and then they grew worſe, and many a blow I received upon that account which I bore patiently, and I can truly ſay I never repented my going, nor refrained, until Wars came in <hi>England;</hi> Then was the Flock of God ſcattered abroad as ſheep without a Shepherd, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about like a Partridge on the Mountains, and many were killed with the Sword, and often put to the flight, which made me and others que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether God had not forſaken his own People, becauſe he did not deliver them out of their enemies hands; then the enemies of the Lord did rejoice both within and without, as if all had been their own, then the Seed of God ſuffered in <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes were ſlain and were made merry over, and then the Seed ſuffered, and the ſeed of the Serpent got on the top, and led me captive at his will; Now take notice the ſame Light I now own, not another, did let me ſee my ſtate that I was run into darkneſs and departed from the Lord, and was in the broad way which leadeth to deſtruction; but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did many ſtrong cryes run through me, ſaying, O that I could but ſee the day I once ſaw; yea, when I have been ſetting up my ſelf in pride, or otherwiſe, I have wiſhed, O that I were in ſuch a condition I was once in, if I had not raggs to cover my nakedneſs; thus I paſſed on
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65082:2"/>wilde and wanton until the wars were ſomething abated, and Lectors were ſet up, and I heard many men, and they held many Opinions, I thought I was the worſt amongſt all, for I was aſhamed of my preſent eſtate, however I left my Companions, and then I poſted up and down after the moſt eminent men in thoſe parts, for I ſoon ſaw the deceit of the Tithe Prieſts and denied them all, yet ſtill I ſaw in my ſelf I was condemned becauſe I did not walk up to what I knew, though many branches were broken off, yet the root ſtill remained, thus was I toſſed from Mountain to Hill and hurried here and there, but none ſpake to my preſent eſtate until I met with one whoſe Name was known unto us by the Name of <hi>James Brown,</hi> who as I underſtand died an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the ſame Truth that he once declared, and to the ſame Light which he once bore Teſtimony, though this is a hard ſaying; but hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a little and conſider you that were with me at the firſt in that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Water-Baptiſm, and feel what I ſay, this man was very low and tender, and had denied himſelf of all his honour and profit in the world, inſomuch that he came to a low eſtate, yet I could not ſee but that he was contented while he was in that condition, could I ſee ſuch an image born up amongſt you as was once in him, I ſhould own it as dear as my life; but feigned humility I deny, mark that, and for his Doctrine, it was the very ſame words which the Meſſengers of the Lord are gone forth with, and I in my meaſure do ſet my ſeal to, though at the firſt I did much oppoſe him, but my foundation could not ſtand, though got very high; as concerning the Light he ſpoke often of it, that it was the Light and Life of men, and that it ſhined in darkneſs, and that it was the true Light that lighteth every one that cometh into the World, and that the Word was within the Mouth and in the Heart, and that Chriſt was within, and he often preſt it to me, that if Chriſt was not within me I was a Reprobate, the which I did believe it was the truth, and that my greateſt enemies were within, I knew it was ſo; then the Serpent raged, and then were Wars and rumours of Wars ſuch as never was before, the Sword of the Lord was drawn to cut down all his enemies, &amp; the book was opened, &amp; all that ever I had done was laid before me, and my Good and evil was all judged, I would have ran any way to have hid my ſelf, or to any one, but I thought none was like me, thus was my condition ſeveral weeks together, I ſought death in that day but I could not find it, <hi>I</hi> would fain have dyed but death fled from me, when day appeared <hi>I</hi> was afraid, and alſo of the night, many were the temptations to end my life, but there was a ſecret power kept me from it, and as <hi>I</hi> kept low <hi>I</hi> heard a voice cry, Juſt and Righteous are the Judgements of the Lord, and as <hi>I</hi> kept in, a hope of deliverance was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65082:3"/>raiſed contrary to that Serpents voice, for he ſaid, it would never be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, ſo yet <hi>I</hi> waited till ſome propheſies aroſe, that Sorrow ſhould endure for a Night, but Joy ſhould come in the Morning, and ſo it was, that as mine Enemies fell, my Soul rejoyced &amp; my hard Heart was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the Lamb got the Victory, and a precious condition <hi>I</hi> did enjoy, and then were the Scriptures pretious to me as <hi>I</hi> came to witneſs to them, and <hi>Sion</hi> was redeemed through judgement as it is at this day; Now this is to inform your mindes that no other Way do <hi>I</hi> own, no other Truth, no other Life, no other Rock, no other Refuge, no other hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place in time of need then <hi>I</hi> owned at that day, my Judgement is the ſame, and my Guide my Teacher, and my Life is the ſame now; Why is this wonder both with Profeſſor and Prophane at my great change? It is nothing elſe but a woman that hath run after many Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, returned to her former Husband again: Now praiſes, praiſes to his great Name for ever, who did not ſhut up his Tender Compaſſion, nor Seal me up for the day of Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Come let us Reaſon together of former Experiences, though it will not be mentioned but to your ſorrow, and call to minde the Lords Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; my Soul was never ſo poured forth with pitty towards you, nor laid ſo naked and bare before you, you that were with me in that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very aforementioned, and many Revilings, Mocks, Scoffs &amp; Reproaches did we bear together, and eſteemed them as great Riches; And did you not know a day of Suffering within you, and drank deep of the Cup of the Lords fury and indignation which you called trouble? And did you not know in ſome meaſure the Warfare, and a daily Croſs in the ſelf-denyal of your own Words, Wayes and Wills, to yea, and nay in your communication, and to few words, and did you not know a more purer Separation from the World then in Words, and Houſes? Sink down and digg deep in your earthly hearts and read me there; Did you not feed on daily bread in your Fathers houſe, and on the Tree of Life, whoſe Leaves healed the Nations? And did you not looſe that pretious eſtate by reaching out after the Tree of Knowledge, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to know more in the Scriptures then your lives could witneſſe? Both Teachers and others, to that of God do I direct you, who ſhall Witneſs for me in the day of the Lords Power, and he that could ſpeak moſt and diſcourſe beſt was moſt eſteemed, and had forgotten the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Paths, and much proving our ſelves to be Saints, when our lives ſhewed before whoſe Servants we were, as <hi>Saul</hi> when the Spirit of the Lord was departed from him, <hi>then honour me before the people,</hi> when he had loſt the Honour that cometh from God, then the image of the Beaſt was ſet up whoſe head was of gold, and the falſe prophet, and he that would
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65082:3"/>not bow unto them, muſt have no communion with us, and they got a cover to cover deceit, as Pride they called Decency, Coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Carefulneſſe and Saving, and Laughter they called rejoycing in the Lord, Fooliſh-jeſting and lying, and anger and Malice, they called Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Failings, Jangling about the meanings of Scriptures, they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Contending for the Faith; But really I could not own theſe things until I was Married, then the Branches that were broken off for many years began to ſprout again, and then was I ſhut out of that Scripture, there be Gods many and Lords many, but to us there is but one God, I durſt not read it, for the witneſſe of God in my Conſcience told me, that I did ſet up in my heart other things beſide the Lord, as Husband and other Riches which ſoon did fall, and now I ſet my Seal to the Apoſtles Words, that Covetouſneſſe is the Root of all evil, the ſame Light I now own did then ſhew me that I was in the Worlds Nature, and did Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me when none elſe did, for when things proſpered I could be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but when my Will was croſſed, anger and peeviſhneſſe grew up; I thought to cover my ſelf, ſaying, all others were in that eſtate, but that Covering was too narrow, though the Adminiſtration of Condemnation is Glorious in its time, yet another eſtate muſt be witneſſed before peace be witneſſed; When I was by my ſelf ſober I ſaw my eſtate, and that there was a great Gulf or a Cloud drawn between the Lord and I, but all this while who could accuſe me without; and often there was brought to a perfect remembrance my former pretious condition, I ſat by the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Babylon</hi> when I remembred <hi>Sion,</hi> then I broke mine heart pouring out my Soul, ſaying, Curſed be the day that ever I taſted of that Fruit that was forbidden, yea I wiſh that my tongue had cloven to the Roof of my Mouth, rather then I ſhould have ſpoke of one Scripture that I could not witneſſe, yea it is a repentance never to be repented of; in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned eſtate I remained; Then I queſtioned my Faith, my hope and my Love, my Repentance, my Meat, Drink and Aparrel, though it was like to others who were called pretious Saints; I knew not what to do nor which way to take, ſometimes I ſaw the Gate of Mercy opened, but no way to enter but through Judgement, I was willing to wait therein, but when I felt it terrible with a mighty croſs to the will of the fleſh, then I would mind another thing; I heard a cry run through me, ſaying, their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants you are to whom you obey, whether in obedience to Righteouſneſs or unrighteouſneſſe; I had no reſt, at laſt I replyed, Ah Lord, do I not keep all thy Commandments, he ſaid nay? I ſaid do I not ſerve thee with Truth of heart? The anſwer was, whom doſt thou ſerve when thou doſt evil; a man cannot ſerve two Maſters, and then my mouth was ſtopt, then I would ſhun thoſe thoughts; then was brought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance how I had read many years before a of man that when sad thoughts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65082:4"/>was in his heart, he would get ſome merry thing to drive them away, I had no reſt, I heard of a people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> I enquired, as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of profeſſors did, what was their Judgement, let never ſo much hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility appear, the anſwer was, that the greateſt profeſſors in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were the greateſt enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt; I do not juſtifie my ſelf, for condemnation hath paſſed on all my good and evil actions, but I find very few profeſſors walk ſo exactly as I did in thoſe dayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things without, though all this did not reach ſo far as the Scribes and Phariſees who were clean on the out ſide, I ſaw it to be ſo, though we called our ſelves the Saints of the Moſt High, yet I ſaid in my ſelf, if the Saints condition was thus, it was a miſerable eſtate, I was weary and heavy laden, I went from meeting to meeting to find out one that was in my condition, all were full, and ſmoothed up one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with words and no Reformation; I durſt not partake of their Bread and Wine, for I ſaw we were ignorant of the Lords Body, I was brought very low and to a waiting condition, what truth I heard declared I own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the reſt I let alone and ſaid little, waiting for the promiſe of the Lord to be fulfilled which I read of in the Scriptures, that the Lord would Teach his People himſelf; in this eſtate I remained almoſt a year, I loved to be by my ſelf, for then I could pour out my Soul before the Lord, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ah teach me the way that I ſhould go, and lead me in the Paths of Righteouſneſſe; Oh when ſhall I ſee the day of thy appearance in fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy promiſe which thou haſt made of old? O why are thy Charret Wheels ſo long a coming; O ſhall I never ſee the day of deliverance? Thus my Soul groaned under a heavy burthen until I met with one of the Lords Meſſengers, and ſore ſufferers for the Teſtimony of Jeſus, whoſe words ſtruck deep through the Earth, and reacht to the witneſſe of God, inſomuch that I durſt not ſpeak a word againſt that thing that I once enjoyed; I owned his words, and ſpake againſt Profeſſors, Prieſts and People, I denyed the Worlds words, Wayes, Faſhions and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms in a great meaſure, I became a reproach, a Proverb and a by-word unto the Countrey round about, and yet the Life of Truth I knew not, my Lovers and Acquaintance ſtood afar off me, my familiar friends were aſhamed to own me, Profeſſors they denied me, as <hi>Philip Farmer</hi> a Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of others did judge me much for denying the Rule, and ſtumbling at Strawes, and leaping over Blocks; and he affirmed that Jeſus Chriſt did bid a woman God ſpeed that was committing Adultery, and that he did bid a man God ſpeed at Plow, and ſaid, he would prove it by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſeveral lies more; Another Teacher judged me for denying the Ordinance, and he affirmed, though Bread was Bread at the Bakers, and Wine was Wine at the Vintners, yet when it came to them it was the Body and Blood of Chriſt. Friends, I do not write this out of any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65082:4"/>evil will that I bear to any mans perſon, the Lord is my witneſſe, but that Truth may appear, and that you may ſee who denied the Rule them or I, or who denied the coming of God, them or I, I did then denie the Rule that they walked by, for all ſuch actors are ſhut out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, though at that time I knew not the right hand from the left, though brought through that before mentioned; <hi>I</hi> would have taken up a reſt there, but the flaming Sword which turned every way cut me down, great were the ſights that I ſaw with mine Eyes, and that which I heard with mine Ears, one woe poured out after another, earth-quakes in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, this was but the beginning of ſorrows, the great and Red Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt behind me, and in that day I knew not God, I durſt not name his Name becauſe I was not departed from iniquity, I knew not what the firſt principle of Religion was, I feared leaſt any ſhould ask a reaſon of my Faith; I cried for the diſquietneſſe of my heart, I curſt the day and the hour my Mother brought me forth, and in that year I did witneſſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> plagued with many plagues before he would let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go, I would have done any thing that was pleaſing in his ſight, but all was accurſed, nothing but Wars and rumours of Wars, many diſpairing thoughts entered into me, I was like one that went from a Lyon and a Bear met him, and leaned upon a wall, and a Serpent bit him, I was pleaded with by Sword and by Fire, yea the Fire burned all the day till I was almoſt conſumed, I went about like a Fool or like one deſtracted, yea if I had been to write but a Note of an outward thing, I could not compoſe it no more then a natural Fool, all my building was decayed, not one ſtone upon another that was not thrown down; I went mourning all the day like a woman that mourneth for her only Son, there was no eye pitied me, but then was the time of love, I heard a voice cry, agree with thy adverſarie quickly whilſt thou art in the way with him, for Judgement am I come into this World, that they which ſee not might ſee, and they which ſee might be made blind; Now praiſes, praiſes to his great Name for ever, who hath made a way in the deep Waters and path in the Sea, for his own Seed to paſſe over, and hath drowned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his great Hoſt, and overwhelmed them all, and delivered <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of many troubles, and hath turned and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned till pure peace and joy is witneſſed in the Land, and I witneſſe his words, who ſaid a woman that is in Travel hath ſorrow becauſe her hour is come, but aſſoon as ſhe is delivered of her Child ſhe remembreth no more the anguiſh for joy; but only for your ſakes is the Father pleaſed to bring to remembrance, and I dare not be ſilent but declare what the Lord hath done for my ſoul, it may be thoſe that are in the Serpents Wiſdom will judge theſe things to be frothy empty things, but really
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65082:5"/>it is that which you muſt all paſs through if ever you come to witneſs a Reſtauration again, although you may create to your ſelves many reſts, yet it is that which will not indure the fire ſeven times to be tried; My Friends, I know the thing, I call you Friends out of tender love and pitty that I bare to you, though I have not found you ſo, yet my love is dear to the Seed of God which is kept under in you. Whether you will hear or forbear I have cleared my Conſcience, for I ſee <hi>Satans</hi> policy, if he can keep men and women from believing in the Light, then his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtands ſure, for the Light diſcovers his dark wayes and works, and leads the Creature out of them by degrees to an innocent eſtate and to a Holy Life.</p>
            <p>Therefore retire your minds into that which ſhews you that you come too ſhort of what you ought to be; You have been long ſweeping with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and hath not made it clean, now learn the Parable of the woman, and ſweep the houſe, for verily there is no other place to find that which you have loſt; Dig deep to find that Pearl of great price, and buy it though it coſt you all you have, do not eſteem the Light a low thing, calling it natural; for verily if you will but wait in it, it will diſcover ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickedneſſe in high places, and ſhew you the ſecret intents of your hearts, this is that light which the Prophet propheſied of, which ſhould lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and old <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> rejoyced to ſee him that the Prophets propheſied of, this is the True Light which <hi>John</hi> bare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of, and whoſoever followed him ſhould not abide in darkneſſe, as he himſelf ſaid, this is he which <hi>Zacharias</hi> propheſied of which ſhould give Light to them that ſit in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death, this is that Light which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid <hi>Shone in a dark place until the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts;</hi> Therefore take heed to it, this is he that ſearcheth the heart and trieth the Reins, and ſheweth to man what is his thoughts, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.13.</p>
            <q>Thus have I in love to all your Souls written of the tender dealings of the Lord to my Soul, as a warning to you that you ſhould no longer reſiſt the loving kindneſſe of the Lord.</q>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the Signe of the Bull and Mouth near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
